Izzy Young collection, 1942-2015
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Izzy Young collection 1942-2015
AFC 2015/040
Izzy Young, 1928-
5,972 items
53 linear feet (133 containers)
88 sound tape reels: analog; 7 and 10 in.
583 photographic prints: black and white, color; various sizes
130 containers
8 objects
28 sound and video discs (CD-R and DVD-R): digital; 4 3/4 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of manuscripts, including correspondence, journals, diaries, scrapbooks, clippings, artwork, and ephemera; photographic prints; and audio recordings comprising the archive of Israel (Izzy) Goodman Young, who was proprietor of the Folklore Center, New York, N.Y. (beginning in 1957), and then, beginning in 1973, of the Folklore Centrum, Stockholm, Sweden. The collection documents the late 1950s and 1960s folk music revival, and Izzy Young's contribution to the scene. Includes documentation about prominent musicians, poets, and dancers, and about concerts, music festivals, and music camps around the United States and in Sweden. Includes articles and writings about Bob Dylan and his musical career, and correspondence with significant figures in the folk music scene, such as Pete Seeger, Mark Moss, and Dick Waterman. Scrapbooks document concerts and other events, including the 1961 Washington Square Park Protest, which followed the New York Police Department's attempt to stop singing in the park. Audio recordings are of radio programs, and concerts that Young promoted, such as those with Hedy West, David Bromberg, Jean Ritchie, Elizabeth Cotten, and many others.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Barretta, Scott--Correspondence.; Bromberg, David, 1945-; Charters, Samuel, 1929-2015.; Cohen, John, 1932-2019.; Cohen, Ronald, 1940- --Correspondence.; Cotten, Elizabeth; Dylan, Bob, 1941-; Gahr, David; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Guthrie, Woody, 1912-1967.; Killen, Louis.; Kupferberg, Tuli; Leadbelly, 1885-1949.; Leventhal, Harold.; Lloyd, A. L. (Albert Lancaster), 1908-1982; Lomax, Alan, 1915-2002.; Marcus, Greil--Correspondence.; Mayo, Margot, 1910-1974.; Ochs, Phil.; Oppenheimer, Joel; Paley, Tom; Reuss, Richard A.--Correspondence.; Ritchie, Jean; Rotolo, Suze--Correspondence.; Seeger, Mike, 1933-2009; Seeger, Mike, 1933-2009.; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014--Correspondence.; Seeger, Toshi--Correspondence.; Siebel, Paul; Silber, Marc.; Smith, Harry Everett, 1923-1991.; West, Hedy; Winston, Winnie; Young, Izzy, 1928-2019; Young, Izzy, 1928-2019.
Organizations
Folklore Center (New York, N.Y.); Folklore Center (New York, N.Y.); Folklore Centrum.; Friends of Old-Time Music.; WBAI Radio (New York, N.Y.); Young Tradition (Musical group)
Subjects
Folk festivals--United States.; Folk music--Sweden.; Folk music--United States.; Folk singers--New York (State)--New York.; Klezmer music--United States.; Popular music--1961-1970.; Protest movements--New York (State)--New York.; Square dancing--United States.
Places
New York (N.Y.)--Social life and customs.; Stockholm (Sweden)--Social life and customs.; Washington Square (New York, N.Y.)
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Diaries.; Ephemera.; Folk music radio programs.; Interviews.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Sound Recordings; III. Graphic Materials; IV. Optical Media; V. Artifacts; VI. Publications.
Journals and scrapbooks arranged chronologically. Binders are organized alphabetically by topic that Izzy Young designated. Correspondence, ephemera, and graphic images described at the folder level. Arrangement reflects the intellectual/chronological order rather than the physical numbering of items.
Acquisition
Izzy Young; 2015.
Accruals
Additional accrual received in January 2020.
Related Material
A related collection is AFC 2017/047, Izzy Young guest register for the Folklore Center, 1966 January 10-11. https://lccn.loc.gov/2017655422 The guest register (in the form of a standard composition notebook) is from an unidentified event at the Folklore Center, and contains 134 names and addresses on 11 pages. The register includes guests such as Harold Anton, Theodore Wilentz, Carol Janeway, Arthur Rosenbaum, Phil Ochs, Duke Miles, Berenice Abbott, Frank Hanley, Ed Sanders, Ted Berrigan, Tuli Kupferberg, Doc Watson, Ralph Rinzler, Israel Young, Herbert Huncke, and others.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access to collection materials may be restricted. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Alternate Form of Material
Digital preservation masters from original sound tape reels.
Biographical Note
Israel (Izzy) Goodman Young was born March 26, 1928 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. In the 1940s, Young fell in love with square dancing through his involvement with Margot Mayo's American Square Dance Group, where he met folk musicians such as Pete Seeger, Oscar Brand, and Reverend Gary Davis. After accumulating a catalog of books about folk music, Young opened the Folklore Center in 1957, a music store and gathering place for the folk music revival scene in Greenwich Village. Young organized and promoted folk music concerts and poetry readings at the Folklore Center and at other venues in New York City. He was a founder of the Friends of Old Time Music, a group which presented concerts of traditional folk musicians in New York City venues. Young also organized what is thought to be Bob Dylan's first formal concert on November 4, 1961 at Carnegie Hall, as well as the early concerts of musicians such as Tim Buckley, Joni Mitchell, and Mississippi John Hurt. He wrote about the folk music scene in his Sing Out! Magazine column, "Frets and Frails," from 1959 to 1969. In 1973, Young emigrated to Stockholm, Sweden, and opened the Folklore Centrum, through which he has organized and promoted cultural events, including Scandanavian folk music and dance events. From the mid-1980s until 2012, Young issued the Folklore Centrum newsletter, a resource for events and commentary about Swedish and American folk music.
Scope and Content
Collection of manuscripts, including correspondence, journals, diaries, scrapbooks, clippings, artwork, and ephemera; photographic prints; and audio recordings comprising the archive of Israel (Izzy) Goodman Young, who was proprietor of the Folklore Center, New York, N.Y. (beginning in 1957), and, beginning in 1973, of the Folklore Centrum, Stockholm, Sweden. The collection documents the late 1950s and 1960s folk music revival, and Izzy Young's contribution to the scene. Includes documentation about prominent musicians, poets, and dancers, and about concerts, music festivals, and music camps around the United States and in Sweden. Includes articles and writings about Bob Dylan and his musical career, and correspondence with significant figures in the folk music scene, such as Pete Seeger, Mark Moss, and Dick Waterman. Scrapbooks document concerts and other events, including the 1961 Washington Square Park Protest, which followed the New York Police Department's attempt to stop singing in the park. Sound recordings in the collection include radio programs, and concerts Young promoted, such as those with Hedy West, David Bromberg, Jean Ritchie, Elizabeth Cotten, Young Tradition, Tom Paley, Mike Seeger, Tuli Kupferberg, and many others. Includes eight pieces of original artwork by Harry Smith, artist, filmmaker, and a friend of Young's.
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts, ca. 1942-2015
  - Subseries A: Journals
    Handwritten journals labelled by year. Sorted chronologically.
    - Journals, 1942-1964, 12 items (Box 127)
      Bound journals as well as loose pages from journals. Includes Young's middle school graduation journal with notes from family members and teachers, as well as a journal written during the time of the Folklore Center's opening.
    - Journals, 1952-1986, 28 items (Box 1)
      Includes journal written by Izzy Young's father, Philip Young. Includes journal with commentary by Izzy Young about the 1963 Newport Folk Festival. Also includes "Concerts 1969" journal with details about the concerts that Izzy organized.
    - Journals, 1955-1968, 16 items (Box 128)
      Interspersed within journals are correspondence, poetry, drawings, fliers, and newspaper clippings. Includes letters from Young to John Cohen, Happy Traum, and Bob Dylan.
    - Miscellaneous journals, 1957-1998, 3 items (Box 9)
      Bound poetry journal and journal including notes about international topics/politics. 1 folder containing "A New Secret History of Folklore U.S.A." by Izzy Young, February 1957. 1 folder containing miscellaneous portions of journals, ca. 1960-1970. 1 folder containing photocopy of Izzy Young's journal titled, Young's anecdotes, ca. 1960-1968. One journal encompassing from 1986-1998.
    - Miscellaneous bound journals, ca. 1966-2001, 15 items (Box 8)
      Includes poetry journal, calendars, address books, and manuscript for Israel G. Young Autobiography, 1928-1938.
    - Journals, 1968-1973, 16 items (Box 129)
      Interspersed within journals are correspondence, poetry, drawings, fliers, and newspaper clippings.
    - Journals, 1978-2008, 7 items (Box 130)
      Includes loose journal pages. Interspersed within journals are correspondence, poetry, drawings, fliers, and newspaper clippings.
    - Journals, 1983-2015, 12 items (Box 132)
    - Journals, 1986-1995, 16 items (Box 2)
      Interspersed within journals are correspondence, poetry, drawings, and newspaper clippings.
    - Journals, 1988-2014, 8 items (Box 131)
    - Journals, 1995-1999, 20 items (Box 3)
      Interspersed within journals are correspondence, poetry, photographs, personal/business contacts, drawings, and newspaper clippings.
    - Journals, 2000-2002, 13 items (Box 4)
    - Journals, 2003-2005, 14 items (Box 5)
      Interspersed within journals are correspondence, poetry, photographs, personal/business contacts, scheduling calendars, ticket stubs, drawings, and newspaper clippings.
    - Journals, 2005-2009, 15 items (Box 6)
    - Journals, 2010-2015, 11 items (Box 7)
  - Subseries B: Scrapbooks
    Scrapbooks compiled, numbered, and notated by Izzy Young.
    - Scrapbook #1, 1959, 1 item (Box 10)
      Written on inside cover: "Folklore Center Scrapbook of Articles on Folkmusic That Appear in Newspapers, Journals of Popular Nature." Includes first preliminary sketch of new sign for Folklore Center by Ray Borgular. Includes newspaper clippings and correspondence (including a letter from Richard Dyer-Bennet).
    - Scrapbook #2, 1960-1962, 1 item (Box 11)
      Includes newspaper clippings, drawings, programs from the Folklore Center, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young.
    - Scrapbook #3, 1962-1963, 1 item (Box 12)
      Includes handwritten notes, folk music news items and annotations by Izzy Young, newspaper clippings, telegrams and correspondence, drawings, "Frets and Frails" columns, fliers and programs.
    - Scrapbook #4, "Talking John Birch Blues", 1963, 1 item (Box 13)
      Lyrics of Bob Dylan song, "Talking John Birch Blues" pasted on page 47 of scrapbook and include notes by Izzy Young. Scrapbook includes newspaper clippings, drawings, concert fliers and programs, and correspondence.
    - Scrapbook #5, 1961-1963, 1 item (Box 14)
      Includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, drawings, fliers and programs, business cards, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young.
    - Scrapbook #6, 1963-1964, 1 item (Box 15)
      Includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, fliers, programs and calendars, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young.
    - Scrapbook #7, 1964, 1 item (Box 16)
    - Scrapbook #8, 1965, 1 item (Box 17)
      Includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, fliers, programs, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young and others, including a write up by David Grisman about the Blue Grass Festival at Roanoke. Information about the Sing-In for Peace Committee.
    - Scrapbook #9 and #10, 1965-1966, 2 items (Box 18)
      Scrapbook #9 includes newspaper clippings, correspondence, fliers, programs, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young and others. Includes letter from Sing-In for Peace Committee. Scrapbook #10 includes handwritten notes/correspondence by Izzy Young and others, such as Dick Waterman, Patrick Sky, and Stefan Grossman. Includes program about Hedy West that is translated into Hebrew.
    - Scrapbook #11 and #12, 1966-1967, 2 items (Box 19)
      Scrapbook #11 includes newspaper clippings, programs, correspondence, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young. Includes press release about Doc and Merle Watson's State Department tour. Scrapbook #12 includes a Folklore Center Folk Festival program with performances by Hedy West, Rosalie Sorrels, John Hammond, Joni Mitchell, and many others.
    - Scrapbook #13 and #14, 1968, 2 items (Box 20)
      Scrapbook #13 includes newspaper clippings, fliers and programs, press releases, correspondence, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young. Scrapbook #14 includes excerpts from Folklore Center newsletters, reviews of the 1968 Newport Folk Festival, and a ticket and program from the Newport Folk Festival.
    - Scrapbook #15, 1969, 1 item (Box 21)
      Includes newspaper clippings, fliers and programs, press releases, correspondence, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young. Includes excerpts from Folklore Center newsletters, and Sing Out! Magazine.
    - Scrapbook of trip to New York City, 2005, 1 item (Box 22)
      Includes newspaper clippings, advertisements, fliers, and handwritten notes by Izzy Young.
    - Washington Square Park protest scrapbook, 1961, 1 item (Box 23)
      Oversized scrapbook about the Washington Square Protest, following the New York Police Department's attempt to stop singing in the park. Includes news clippings, correspondence, and other materials related to the event. Restored by Mitch Blank in 2009.
  - Subseries C: Topical binders
    Topical binders sorted alphabetically by title, assigned by Izzy Young.
    - The Almanac Singers, 1941-1942; Hall of Fame, 1996; Hard Traveling, 1996; Article on Copyright, 1960-1990, 2 items (Box 24)
      Includes Pete Seeger's history of the Alamanac Singers, 1987, and the program from Hard Traveling, a Woody Guthrie event put on by the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame and Museum, and the Woody Guthrie Archives. Article on Copyright binder includes articles about copyright law, public domain, and folk songs.
    - Articles: Seeger, Lomax, 2003-2006, 1 item (Box 25)
      Articles about Pete Seeger, Bruce Springsteen, and Alan Lomax.
    - Articles, more, 1959-2006, 1 item (Box 26)
      Articles/writings by and about Izzy Young. Includes writings about Bob Dylan and an excerpt from the Folk Music Guide USA (November 1959).
    - Articles, various (unsorted!), newly filed, April 2012, ca. 1973-2010, 1 item (Box 27)
      Includes writings by and about Izzy Young.
    - Artiklar on Izzy, T.O.M., 1999, ca. 1974-1999, 1 item (Box 28)
      Includes articles about Izzy Young in English and Swedish.
    - Bibliographies, scholarly articles, ca. 1934-1991, 1 item (Box 29)
      Includes articles about John and Alan Lomax and a Folklore Center reprint of "Folk Song Style" by Alan Lomax from American Anthropologist (2 copies).
    - Book reviews, articles, obituarites, etc.; Brev, ca. 1963-2012, 2 items (Box 30)
      Includes articles about Lead Belly and Alan Lomax in English and Swedish. Brev binder primarily includes correspondence.
    - Brev, ca. 1987-1988, ca. 1984-1988, 1 item (Box 31)
      Primarily includes correspondence.
    - Brev, 1989, ca. 1984-1989, 1 item (Box 32)
      Includes correspondence to/from Marc Silber, Mike Seeger, and Happy Traum, as well as correspondence regarding music sales and royalties.
    - Brev, 1994-1995; Brev Norden, ca. 1994-1996, 2 items (Box 33)
      Includes correspondence and hand written notes by Izzy Young.
    - Tim Buckley; Carol, 1967-2009, 2 items (Box 34)
      Includes articles and correspondence about Tim Buckley, and a 1967 writing by Izzy Young. Carol binder includes correspondence between Izzy Young and Carol Greene.
    - Professor Ronald Cohen, projects, 1989-1994, 1 item (Box 35)
      Primarily includes correspondence between Ronald Cohen and Izzy Young.
    - Professor Cohen, NYC folk museum, 1999, 1998-2000, 1 item (Box 36)
      Primarily includes correspondence between Ronald Cohen and Izzy Young. Also includes meeting information about the proposed Folk Music Museum in Greenwich Village.
    - Prof R[onald]. C[ohen]. II, 1994-1996, 1 item (Box 37)
    - Ron Cohen III; Cohen Young letters, Sept. 1997, 1997-1999, 2 items (Box 38)
    - Copyright notices, introductions, title pages; Copyright, more info., 1995-2012, 2 items (Box 39)
      Includes writings about Lead Belly and copyright, including an excerpt from "Negro Folk Songs as Sung by Lead Belly," (1936) by John and Alan Lomax and a copy of the 1937 agreement between John and Alan Lomax and Lead Belly.
    - Diverse mm att katologisera; Diverse studies, ca. 1960-1996, 2 items (Box 40)
      Includes concert fliers, Folkways Records catalog, clippings, and copy of Bob Dylan drawing from Izzy Young's Feb. 22, 1962 notebook. 3 photographs removed from this binder and placed in Series III (Bob Dylan portrait by Bertil Hagert, Izzy Young photograph by Ed Grazda, and Big Joe Williams photograph by David Gahr and 3 slides removed and placed in Series III (slides of Bob Dylan drawing in Izzy Young's notebook). Diverse Studies binder includes academic articles about ethnomusicology and folk music and indentity. Also includes correspondence.
    - Bob Dylan, 1980-1990, 1 item (Box 41)
      Includes clippings about Bob Dylan written in English and Swedish.
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 1991-1996, 1 item (Box 42)
      Includes clippings and articles about Bob Dylan written in English and Swedish.
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 1997, 1 item (Box 43)
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 1998-2000, 1 item (Box 44)
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 2001, 1 item (Box 45)
      Includes clippings and articles about Bob Dylan written in English, Swedish, and Hebrew.
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 2002-2003, 1 item (Box 46)
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 2004, 1 item (Box 47)
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 2005, 1 item (Box 48)
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 2006-2007, 1 item (Box 49)
    - Bob Dylan Pressklipp, 2009-2010; Dylan Tom 2007? Misc., 1968, 1998-2010, 2 items (Box 50)
      Includes clippings and articles about Bob Dylan written in English and Swedish. Dylan Tom 2207? Misc. binder includes correspondence filed by topic/correspondent, which Izzy Young designated. Topics include 1960s folk revival and Bob Dylan. Includes "two sheets out of an old lined notebook," from Dec. 28, 1968.
    - Even Dozen Jug Band; Film - TV, sonnet, Downing, osv, 1963, 1987-1994, 2 items (Box 51)
      Includes Izzy Young's handwritten journal pages with notes about concerts he was organizing, contact names and information, and Young's general notes about the music and performers. Includes a 1994 note from Izzy Young on the first page of binder about finding these pages in his mother's basement. Film - TV, sonnet, Downing, osv binder includes correspondence, including from Jim Downing regarding a documentary film, and correspondence to and from Pete and Toshi Seeger.
    - Folklore Center, 1957-1968; Folklore Center, and Friends of Old Time Music, 1969-, 1957-1974, 2 items (Box 52)
      Includes original fliers and programs for concerts organized by the Folklore Center and the Friends of Old Time Music, including with Oscar Brand, Tom Paley, Barry Kormfeld, Reverand Gary Davis, Jack Elliot, Clarence Ashley, Big Joe Williams, Victoria Spivey, Gus Cannon, Furry Lewis, Hobart Smith, Doc Watson, Joseph Spence, Lou Killen, and Mike Seeger.
    - Frets and Frails, 1959-; Gamla for Artiklar, 1959-2007, 2 items (Box 53)
      Includes Izzy Young's Sing Out! Magazine column, "Frets and Frails," as well as the Folklore Revisited column. Gamla for Artiklar binder includes fliers and other ephemera advertising concerts, a typed interview with David Grisman and with Phil Ochs and Tuli Kupferberg, and typed and handwritten journal entries.
    - Gellert - new material, old material, and correspondence; Ralph J. Gleason, 1939-2004, 2 items (Box 54)
      Includes correspondence with Steve Garabedian, Richard Reuss, and Joe Hickerson. Includes a 1939 song book from the collection of Lawrence Gellert, "Me and My Captain": Negro Songs of Protest. Ralph J. Gleason binder includes articles by jazz and pop music critic, Ralph Gleason.
    - Woody Guthrie and the Swedish Left; Irene, 1977, 1999, 2 items (Box 55)
      Correspondence and articles. Includes article on Guthrie in American Exile newsletter and a piece by Izzy Young about Woody Guthrie in Broadside issue number 87. Irene binder includes sheet music for "Good night, Irene." Included a 45rpm disc of "Good Night, Irene" by Lead Belly on Playboy Records (50028).
    - Lead Belly correspondence, 1995-1996, 1 item (Box 56)
      Primarily includes correspondence about Lead Belly, Alan Lomax, and copyright issues. Correspondents include Dick Weissman and Sean Killeen of Lead Belly Society.
    - Library of Congress, Folk Archive finding aid; Lomax, 1983-2005, 2 items (Box 57)
      LC Folk Archive Finding Aids and Reference Aids from 1983-1990. Lomax binder includes correspondence and articles critiquing Alan Lomax's work.
    - Lomax Anew, ca. 1958-2004, 1 item (Box 58)
      Includes correspondence, Lead Belly sheet music, and other writings about Alan Lomax and Lead Belly.
    - Miscellaneous articles, interviews, Izzy, 1957-2005, 1 item (Box 59)
      Includes articles, writings, and typed journal entries by Izzy Young. Includes articles from Promenade magazine by the American Square Dance Group. Also includes articles, writings about Izzy. Removed photograph from 1957 opening of Folklore Center and placed in Graphic Images series.
    - Miscellaneous articles on American musicians; Miscellaneous collections studies lists, etc., etc., ca. 1968-2005, 2 items (Box 60)
      Includes email correspondence, Folk Roots articles, articles/writings about folk musicians, and materials about calling square dances and contra dances.
    - Miscellaneous letters, articles; Miscellaneous revival materials: notebooks, letters, press cuttings, 1959-1991, 2 items (Box 61)
      Includes clippings about folk music and fliers for concerts. Miscellaneous revival materials: notebooks, letters, press cuttings binder includes a typed conversation between Izzy Young and Phil Ochs, articles about folk musicians (Dave Van Ronk, John Fahey) and about the Washington Square Park protest.
    - More old mail; My journal, 1960-1962, 2007, 2 items (Box 62)
      Printed email correspondence. Includes correspondence with Suze Rotolo and Ann Charters. My journal binder includes Izzy Young's typed journal entries, 1960-1962.
    - My journal, typewritten; NY UPPL press mm, invitations, konsertar mm, ca. 1962-2010, 2 items (Box 63)
      Izzy Young's typed journal entries. NY UPPL press mm, invitations, konsertar mm binder includes email correspondence, newspaper clippings, and ephemera in Swedish.
    - A new attempt to keep up with email, 2006-04, 1 item (Box 64)
      Printed email correspondence and a couple of handwritten correspondence. Includes correspondence with Elijah Wald, John Szwed, and Rani Singh.
    - New correspondence, 2008, 1 item (Box 65)